Chris Howarth

I am a First-Class Honours Computing and I.T graduate with 3 years of software engineering experience through a leading digital-first public service broadcaster. I am a highly organised and driven individual enjoying a challenging and rewarding career in software engineering. I am currently seeking a software engineer or cyber security position in an organisation that likes to promote innovation and will support me while I build upon my existing skills.

Relevant Work History

Software Engineer – BBC Live

BBC

Aug 2024 – Present

- BBC Live provides a consistent user experience for live events across the BBC website for Sport, News, Radio & Music and a growing number of tv events such as Springwatch. It brings audio and video content (live streams, highlights) together with key moments and live text commentary into a single page.
- Monitored system performance and reliability across live service, ensuring high availability for millions of users
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams including product, UX, legal, secops and analysts to deliver high-impact solutions that conform to data governance, security, and compliance standards.
- **Ensured code quality and maintainability** through automated testing, CI/CD pipelines, and DevOps best practices.
- Documented technical solutions clearly and comprehensively for internal use and future development.
- Worked on experimentation and A/B testing, delivering and evaluating new features on BBC Live pages to enhance user experience and engagement.
- Worked on tickets to maintain and improve product health, including bug fixes, performance enhancements, and refactoring legacy code.

Graduate Software Engineer

BBC

Sept 2022 – Aug 2024

- Joined at the level of a junior software engineer
- Completed rotations in different departments the BBC to get a broad understand of the technologies and frameworks used to deliver a first-class customer service
- Teams worked across
 - 1. Sport Web Data Full stack data manipulation and presentation role
 - 2. Sport App (iOS and Android) Mobile native app development role
 - 3. BBC Live Full stack/Front end web live experience role
 - 4. BBC Webcore Platform CI/CD, infrastructure as code and AWS role
- Taken ownership of various tickets relating to front and backend work
- Led and organised meetings with colleagues from different areas of the organisation to develop a better understand of the objectives of certain areas of work
- Arranged code reviews for work that I had completed to release to the production environment with minimal issues
- Worked with team members to resolve urgent outages that effected the customer experience
- Gained experience of working with AWS, Jenkins and other bespoke backend software unique to the BBC
- Currently working within the BBC Web Platform Team, which is responsible for the deployment of primary BBC frameworks with native AWS technologies

- Developed various front-end components while working with the BBC Sport Data team and BBC Live team using JavaScript, React and Typescript
- Previously worked with BBC Sport Mobile team, gaining experience working with typescript, Swift, Kotlin and various other technologies and procedures relevant to mobile app development.
- Member of the BBC Security Champions network and attend bi-weekly meetings provided by the internal security Guild
- Completed courses provided by the BBC academy in Test-Driven Development, Advanced Typescript, Swift, and Threat Modelling.

Education And Qualifications

B.Sc. (Hons) Computing & I.T

Open University

2019 - 2022

- Achieved a First-class Honours
- Included Cisco Networking (CCNA1, CCNA2 and CCNA3) and Cisco DevOps
- Followed a software and data analyst route
- ACHIEVED DISTINCTION GRADES in 9 of 12 modules
- Selection of modules already completed: Algorithms and Data Structures (1st), Web Technologies(1st), Object-orientated Java(1st), Cisco networking (1st), Data Management and Analysis (1st)

B.Sc. (Hons) Forensic Psychology

UCLAN, Preston

2002 - 2005

- Grades: 2:2 achieved at end of course.
- Selection of Modules Completed: Psychological Enquiry (2:1), I.T and Study Skills (1st), Methods in Statistical Analysis (1st), Dissertation (2:1)

A Levels

Turton Sixth Form, Bolton

1999 - 2001

• Studied: Information Technology (B), Mathematics (D), Physics (E)

GCSEs

Turton High School, Bolton

1994 - 1999

• 9 GCSE's at grades B and above, Including Mathematics (A), English (A), English Literature (A), Dual Science (A)

Previous Work History

Landlord & Property Developer Self-Employed, Bolton

June 2016 - 2020

- Managing refurbishments of run-down properties
- Employing and organising tradesmen to complete work promptly
- Organising agencies to value properties and find tenants when applicable
- Managing any ongoing maintenance of properties

Retail Business and Cafe Owner Self Employed, Bolton

Dec 2011 – June 2016

- Dealing with and selling to a large variety of customers on a day-to-day basis
- Maintaining high standards of cleanliness and service
- Strict stock control and inventory management
- Purchasing and negotiating prices with a variety of suppliers
- Upsetting and maintaining a positive attitude daily
- Dealing with customer complaints in a timely, friendly and efficient manner
- Handling various orders via email and phone
- Answering regular customer queries regarding products that were listed online
- Maintaining and updating product listings
- Dealing with any customer refunds and issues
- Communicating with several suppliers and delivery companies to ensure a timely service for the customer

Customer Service Adviser Co-operative Insurance, Manchester July 2007 – Nov 2011

- Dealing with incoming calls regarding home and motor insurance
- Logging all calls and updating systems as required
- Promoting the features and benefits of various products and their suitability to each customer
- Achieving targets in a sales driven environment while maintaining a high level of customer service
- Using Selling and talking positive skills to up-sell products to customers, resulting in very high sales conversion rates

Area Organiser

First Call Healthcare, Bolton

August 2006 – May 2007

- Managing and monitoring a team of carers to provide home care in the community
- Conducting risk assessments and implementing care plans in clients' homes
- Staff Appraisals and client reviews
- Recruitment and interviewing potential new staff
- Updating various spreadsheet and company databases
- Organising staff rotas
- Training current staff to maintain high levels of care

Key Skills

- Front-end Development: I have a good understanding of JavaScript, Typescript, React, and the concepts of functional programming. I have developed various components as part of teams within the BBC that have been release to the production environment. I have also worked previously in mobile app development, specifically using swift and iOS.
- Back-end Development: I have intermediate knowledge of the Python and Java programming languages (I achieved excellent grades in OOP during my degree). I have also worked with several AWS technologies, including Codebuild, Codepipeline, Cloud formation, the AWS CDK, Cloudwatch, AWS lambdas, Step functions, S3 and Cloudtrail.
- Customer Service: Most of my working history has involved some level of customer

service. I have often been the first point of contact for a customer regarding any queries or complaints. During the last 4 years I have prided myself on delivering an excellent and friendly level of customer service.

- Sales: Have developed excellent sales skills in my previous position at CIS and have received training on talking and selling positive. This has resulted in a friendly sales service in which I believe I build an excellent rapport with the customer before selling a product which best suits their needs.
- Communication & People Management: I am a confident and effective communicator of information. I developed these skills in previous roles in management, both when self-employed and as an area organizer. I have experience dealing with individuals from a variety of cultural and generational backgrounds.
- Organisation and Flexibility: Excellent organisational skills which I have demonstrated in every role I have had. These skills have been particularly useful during my current studies to become a software engineer.
- Other I.T. Frequently use several Microsoft Office programs such as Word, Excel, Access
 and Power point. Also have experience of Oracle and bespoke programs such as Esentinel. Extensive knowledge of statistical packages such as SPSS, and regular use of a
 variety of email clients such as Outlook. Completed courses in Spreadsheet Applications
 and Word Processing.

Additional Certificates

(Awarded through Open University)

• Certificated of Higher Education in Computing and IT

(Awarded through UCLan)

- Word Processing
- Spreadsheet Applications

(Awarded through Manchester City Council)

- Managing Health & Safety Awareness and Risk Assessment
- No Secrets; Signs and Symptoms of Abuse
- First Aid-Emergency (*Expired*)
- Cultural & Religious Awareness Training
- Level 2 Food Hygiene (*Expired*)

Interests

- Keen football fan and play for a local football team every Wednesday
- Huge video game fanatic. I enjoy most genres of video games, with a particular interest in RPG or Action-Adventure games.

• Enjoy keeping fit by swimming and am currently a member of a gym. I enjoy maintaining high levels of fitness and plan to run the Great Manchester Run in the future.

Additional Information

- Full Clean Driving License
- Excellent Health Record

References available upon request